Guide to the Boswell Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
The business and political correspondence is particularly interesting. Major correspondents include Archibald Campbell, Earl of Argyll; Alexander Bruce of Broomhall; Bishop Gilbert Burnet; William Douglas, Duke of Hamilton; Elizabeth Murray, Duchess of Lauderdale; Sir Archibald Primrose; John Leslie, Duke of Rothes; Cornelius van Aerssen van Sommelsdyck; and Sir John Werden, secretary to the Duke of York.
Few letters pre-date the Restoration. Four letters by Robert Bruce of Broomhall describe the fears and rumors in Edinburgh as Cromwell's army moved north, including a report that it was "strook with leprosy" and that Fairfax "would not ingage offensively agaynst us from a Covenant principall." In 1656 Argyll (then Lord Lorne) notified Bruce that he had been arrested by order of Monck but assured him that "no action of mine can do you harm." The earliest letters by Cornelius van Aerssen van Sommelsdyck, all in French, contain much political news and speculation, covering the Low Countries and France as well as England (Box 101, folder 1850).
Kincardine was both a political ally of the Duke of Lauderdale and an opponent of religious persecution, a position that grew difficult to maintain as the government became steadily more repressive during the 1670s. Fortunately, much of Kincardine's surviving correspondence dates from this period. The party maneuverings and religious disputes are well-documented in the letterbooks of Gilbert Burnet, the Duchess of Lauderdale, the Duke of Hamilton, and Kincardine's own draft letters to the Duke of York.
Burnet's letters date from between 1660 and 1673, although most are from the early 1670s. They describe his fears for the Established Church and the extent of infighting among the King's ministers over both policy and patronage. Several letters employ a number substitution system for proper names which has not been decoded. Also included in this letterbook are questions for the visitors of the University of Glasgow and Burnet's own proposals for modifications in church government, which he hoped "may gain the favour of many sober persons, at least stop their mouths."
The most complete political information is found in a letterbook docketed by Lord Auchinleck as "Letters from the Dutchess of Lauderdale to my grandfather." The letters date from 1668 to the mid-1670s, with many undated, and several employ a word substitution system for proper names. They contain extremely detailed analyses of the political climate; descriptions of Parliamentary debates and Privy Council sessions; defenses of Lauderdale's actions and policies; and strongly-worded advice to Kincardine about his speeches, conversations, and alliances. One letter, for example, contains a defense of Lauderdale's proroguing of the 1673 Parliament: "What is itt that hes raised the oppisition he hes met with, and mastered heere, but his duty?" (Box 100, folder 1840).
Kincardine testified before that Parliament concerning his profits from the salt excise and described the attacks on him and other excise-holders as "outcries.. .by 5 or 6 lords who do not use to speak much out of a tavern." (Box 100, folder 1839). He resigned the gift to aid the government, instead pursuing the gift of an East India shipwreck, as much of his correspondence at this time reveals (Box 101, folder 1860).
The problem of the conventicles, however, drew more and more of Kincardine's attention, as well as the government's. Primrose's letters from 1673 and later warn continually that "the fanaticks are in open rebellion" and the proposed religious settlement is being rejected. Argyll's letters contain frequent references to the government's harsh policies. In August 1669, for example, he complained that the laws were too severe on dissenting ministers: "those in Argyll are generaly turned land laberers." Five years later, he described the oaths he was expected to administer to his tenants: "if I had beene parrmptoer I had turned them to the hills or other sort of feild conventicles."
The record of Kincardine's break with official policy can be found in the two surviving drafts of a 1675 letter to the Duke of York which outline his disapproval of a plan to make landlords responsible for their non-conforming tenants. After pointing out the impossibility of the task and the difficulty of forcing scrupulous consciences, he concluded: "It did appear to me to be very much agaynst law that any man should be punnyshed for the fault of another which was not in his power to prevent." Less than a year later, Kincardine was dismissed from the Privy Council along with the Duke of Hamilton.
The collection also includes family correspondence. Kincardine married Veronica van Aerssen van Sommelsdyck in 1659, and there are many letters from her relatives, mostly in French, containing general family news, current rumors, and discussions of religious topics. A smaller letterbook holds the couple's letters to their eldest son Charles, who was traveling on the Continent in the late 1670s. These are filled with affectionate advice on subjects ranging from the dangers of Popery and the importance of Greek to Charles's dancing and fencing lessons: "Do not care though they should laugh at you, for you must do those things ill before you do them well and it is no shame." Both parents demanded more frequent letters and Kincardine offered instructions on composition, warning him that "you are to write just as you speake and not to use any affected stile which is very ridiculous."
More information on Kincardine's family life and public career can be found in Personal Papers, folders 1863-1904. Included are Kincardine's 1657 passport to Bremen, signed by General Monck; his commissions as a Captain of Horse and a Lord of the Treasury; the royal tack of the salt excise and his summons before Parliament; and a warrant, apparently unexecuted, creating him Earl of Forth. Folders 1890-92 hold his Privy Council papers: a 1674 appointment; a stitched manuscript of "Papers Relating to Scots Affairs Especially Trades and Manufactures," all written between 1660 and 1666, on such topics as the formation of a trading company for wine and the rules of the Scottish staple. "Reasons...for suppreysing feild conventicles" is the Council's response to a petition by Kincardine in 1675. It is a denunciation of "Phanatick Ministers" and their traitorous followers, and concludes that "it is no small greefe to his Majesties servants here not only to meet with opposition at home, but with misrepresentations abroad." Kincardine's docket notes that he received it "from his Majesties hand."
Other papers include three folders of detailed inventories of the furnishings at Culross, two in the hand of Lady Betty Bruce Boswell; a "Compendium Logicum" in Kincardine's hand; and the 1682 ratification of the gift of the East India shipwreck. Kincardine's marriage contract and provisions, along with later papers concerning Lady Kincardine's life-rents, can be found in folders 1882-88. These seem to indicate that the Kincardine estate was badly impoverished by the time of the Earl's death, which happened shortly after the death of the apparent heir, Charles, Lord Bruce.
Kincardine's second son Alexander succeeded him as third Earl of Kincardine. He was already blind and perhaps mentally disturbed, suggesting that the instability of the first Earl had reappeared, perhaps augmented by weakness in the Sommelsdyck line. (Lady Kincardine's niece, Lady Bellomont, "ran lunatick," and several of her sisters, in Lord Auchinleck's words, "never married and lived much retired from the world.") With the exception of a 1693 letter describing the Christian death of Lord George Douglas, the few papers of the third Earl relate to the financial difficulties of the estate, which had fallen into the hands of trustees. Box 109, folder 1910, contains the 1703 disposition of most of it, including Culross, to William Cochrane of Ochiltree. The following year Queen Anne granted the Earl a pension of £ 300, but he died shortly thereafter.
More information concerning Alexander can be found in the Lady Betty Bruce Boswell section of Series XV, which contains the papers of his youngest sister, who married James Boswell in 1704. She cared for her brother until her marriage, and her concern over his condition is reflected in her correspondence. The collection includes many letters from the Rev. George Mair and the Rev. George Munro, an Episcopal minister of Culross. The Rev. James Aird of Toryburn also composed religious messages for her to read to her brother "if he be able." (Box 105, folder 1921) All of these letters are primarily concerned with religious and devotional topics, and are interesting not only as examples of pastoral counseling by ministers of different denominations but also as demonstrations of the use of theological ideas in the interpretation of mental illness.
Alexander is also a frequent subject in the letters of her two older sisters, Lady Mary Bruce Cochrane and Lady Anne Bruce Murray (Box 104, folders 1917, 1920). In addition to his illness, the sisters discussed Lady Mary's suit to succeed her brother as heir of line, the family's financial difficulties, and the lives, activities, interests and illnesses of their husbands and children. Lady Mary's letters contain much information on James Boswell, who frequently stayed with her during law term in Edinburgh, as well as suggestions that Lady Betty join him to nurse him. In 1728 she reported that "Auchinlek is so oftenn tendur and ille...he has cryed as much of his pain as ever...it is gravell." There are also references to her difficulties with her own children and husband, whom she describes as "not only sinfull but sadly scandulus"; consolation letters on the sickness and death of children and relatives; and much religious discussion.
There are fewer letters from Lady Anne, who died in 1705. In addition to the normal family news, her letters concern the legal and political difficulties of her husband, Sir David Murray, as well as her own ill-health. The letterbook concludes with letters by some of her children and other Murray relatives, mostly speaking of family unhappiness over Sir David's estrangement from them.
Box 104, folder 1914 contains a large letterbook filled with letters by Veronica van Sommelsdyck's sister, Lady Auverquerque. The subjects of the letters, which are all in French, include London social news, information about the author's immediate family and her relatives in Holland, religion, and family business dealings. The letterbook also contains letters in English from her physicians describing her last illness and death and the unfortunate fate of her daughter Lady Bellomont, who had to be confined to a madhouse.
Lady Betty's religious interests are amply documented in several manuscript collections of devotional literature located in Box 105. The individual pieces are extremely varied and include poems; letters of counsel; guides to meditation; Scriptural commentaries; sermons; conversion and deathbed accounts; theological instruction; and hymns. Several pieces are French in origin and language and are connected to the Quietists Antoinette Bourignon and Pierre Poiret, whose teachings enjoyed a brief and controversial popularity in eighteenth-century Scotland. Another figure of controversy, the Rev. James Hogg of Carnock, is represented by a copy of his diary and a transcript of his answers before the Synod of Fife in 1723. A collection of "devot pieces" by the Rev. James Aird of Toryburn includes inspirational letters; "Observations of Monsieur de Renty;" "the most edifying passages in the history of Maria Magdelena;" and a long "Treatise of Adhering to God."
None of these miscellanies has yet been studied in detail, but the sources of the texts appear to be extremely varied. For example, "Ane Account of the conversion of Jean Livingston, Lady Warriston, who was executed for the murder of her husband 1600," was first published by the Roxburghe Club in 1825 in a somewhat different text. "Ane account of Mris Sarah Wight her temptations and deliverance" is derived, with major alterations and omissions, from The Exceeding Riches of Grace Advanced..., published in London in 1647. Several works are attributed to Scottish authors, including a "Call to Come to Christ," patterned on Marlowe's "Come Live With Me," and said to be the work of a Lady Culross. Many of the sermons are identified by author and by the occasion when they were preached.
Box 106 contains a small amount of Lady Betty's other personal papers, mostly contracts and deeds concerning her inheritances from her mother and brother.
Section 3 of Series XV, James Boswell, consists of all estate and family papers not exclusively Lady Betty's and fills Boxes 107-130. Most of his papers, including the correspondence, concern the business affairs of this lawyer and landowner. There are letters concerning the payment of debts, disputed points of contracts, and the schedules of meetings. There is one letter to Alexander, his oldest son, written during his wife's last illness while Alexander was away on business: "As to your comeing...I beelieve your beeing in the countrey is very usefull and our business now requires it. But then when I consider how much itt is our duty to prepare this jewell which is now likely to bee taken away...I will write on this more tomorrow." (Box 109, folder 1962)
That James shared his wife's religious interests is apparent in the letters he received from Sir David Hamilton (Box 109, folder 1965). Physician to Queen Anne, he was the brother of Anna Hamilton, James's mother. In addition to news of family business transactions and political events, his letters contain many discussions of religious subjects and direct spiritual advice. Bound with these are several shorter notes to Lady Betty.
Other personal papers include ten folders of financial papers, mostly processes of debts owed to or purchased by James; his 1690 apprenticeship contract with Robert Crawfurd of Crawfurdstown, which was for two years and cost 200 marks; his own marriage contract and provisions and the contracts of three of his four sisters; and a "Testamentary View of the Estate," drawn up around the time of his death. Box 110, folder 1994 contains a small manuscript of the Boswell family history down to the time of David the sixth laird, which is closely related to the manuscript in James's own hand found in Series II.
The farming of the barony itself is amply documented in a complete run of rental books; household, dairy, stock, and grain accounts; tacks and receipts; and miscellaneous notes concerning liming, crop rotations, and planting. The barony court book (Box 107, folder 1944), is filled with injunctions to tenants to plant trees and clear dykes, as well as denunciations of them for failing to provide the services they owed as rent and for breaking the peace. James still received a substantial amount of rent in kind well into the 1740s, although he was apparently less successful in collecting labor services. The tacks for individual lands found in Land Records tell the same story. Many of the earlier estate papers are in the hand of Lady Betty Bruce, while the later ones are often in Alexander Boswell's hand, who seems to have worked closely with his father on barony matters.
Other examples of this apparent co-operation can be found in the Land Purchases papers. Alexander often acted as his father's agent on purchases, and in some cases it is almost impossible to distinguish between lands bought by Alexander in his own name and his father's purchases. It is clear that both men were devoted to re-building the estate, and the twelve boxes of Land Purchases papers in this series are testimony to James's success.
Boxes 113-14 contain the progress of the writs of Drumfork and Ballangape, James's first major purchase (1714). Of particular interest are the charter and sasine awarded Mungo Reid by Melrose Abbey; a copy of the 1687 marriage contract of Margaret Dalrymple and Adam Aird of Catrine; an extremely lengthy series of processes for debt from 1658 to 1712; and tacks of the farms on the lands written by Adam Aird and turned over to the new owner.
The Howieson purchase is the general name for a group of lands sold to James in the 1730s by Richard Howieson. The role played by debt in Scottish land transfers can be easily seen in this purchase, as folders 2089-90 contain accounts and correspondence relating to Howieson's imprisonment for debt.
The papers for the lands of Lindsayhill and Logan fill Box 117 and continues into Box 118. There are two folders of inventories of the writs, followed by the progress, which fills folders 2137-72. There are several early Melrose charters and sasines, as well as two Papal confirmations Lindsayhill and Logan is also the first example in the collection of an extremely complex type of progress, in which paired or grouped lands are sometimes disposed of together and sometimes separately, or even disposed of at the same time but in two different manners. Repeated over several generations, these procedures tended to bring about confusion over matters of ownership and superiority, and this too can sometimes be traced in the records.
James's acquisition of the barony of Trabeoch was perhaps complicated by the fact that it was the property of his brother-in-law, William Cochrane of Ochiltree, and had been disposed of on a redeemable bond. In fact, one note on Trabeoch's valuation in 1727 points out that "there hath not any care been taken to improve the ground and augment the rents because it might encourage Mr. Cochrane to redeem them and sell them at a greater price." In addition to material on the complex financial transactions among the relatives, the progress includes a 1644 roll docketed "Loudon's right to the barony of Trabeoch"; the marriage contract of William, Lord Cochrane and Euphame Scot; and the 1690 disposition by Loudoun. There is also a separate progress for the lands of Barrenhill from 1554 to 1671 when they were incorporated into Trabeoch, and this contains two folders of tacks dating from 1657-61 (Box 123, folders 2272-73). Finally, folders 2277-82 hold papers concerning the valuation and disjoining of the baronies of Trabeoch and Ochiltree between 1737 and 1743.
The purchase of Tarreoch and Boighead is another "linked purchase." While there are only two sixteenth-century documents concerning these lands, the progress is unusually full for the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries, including a marriage contract; a disposition based on Sir John Cochrane's 1688 forfeiture of his lands; and fifteen folders of papers dealing with James's efforts to clear the claims of other creditors on the last owner and to obtain final title to the properties.
This was often an extremely involved procedure, as can be seen in two "progresses" found in the Land Records section: Braehead and Craikston. The Braehead papers begin with more records of the suits among the Boswell and Mitchell families, and continue with about a dozen folders of fairly obscure transactions between James and the Mitchells. Box 125, folder 2305, holds an undated paper of "Information for James Boswell, Advocate," which sets forth some of the title claims of the Mitchells and possible refutations of them.
The Craikston papers document business dealings between two branches of the Boswell family, James of Auchinleck and the Boswells of the Duncanziemore-Craikston line. Papers preceding 1727 trace the mounting debts of David Boswell of Craikston. After his death a year later, his widow Jean Hunter negotiated with James Boswell concerning the lands, and the later documents treat of the final settling of the deceased's debts and the financial arrangements made by James Boswell for the Craikston family, which included outfitting the eldest son for a voyage to Virginia. (Box 126, folders 2307-08, 2334-38).
Like most of the material in this subseries, the Parish Records are mainly financial records. Located in Box 127, they include hornings of teind delinquents, accounts, receipts and sightings related to repairs on the Auchinleck kirk and manse (folders 2360-69), and the heritor's "call to Mr. David Cooper" as minister in 1731.
ALEXANDER BOSWELL, LORD AUCHINLECK (1707-1782)
Series XVI, Alexander boswell, Lord Auchinleck (1707-1782) is housed in Boxes 131-67 and documents the career of this successful laird and lawyer. Many of Lord Auchinleck's personal papers were moved to Part I, Series II of the Boswell Collection. There are over three boxes of family papers remaining in this series, however, located in folders 2415-78. These include his marriage contract with Euphemia Erskine and seven folders of Erskine family papers; an inventory of dressing plate; an undated commonplace book; and various financial papers, among them his contracts with Dr. Thomas Gillespie, the doctor who treated him for the stone.
Lord Auchinleck's intellectual interests can be seen in his accumulation of genealogical and antiquarian materials (Box 134, folders 2463-64, 2466; Box 135, folder 2477). The most impressive result of these studies, the twelve-volume "Cartulary of the Boswell Family" he commissioned, is now in Boxes 10-13, folders 292-303. There are also copies of a short Greek text on a plaque; "Johannes Luckopius," a satirical poem attributed to Sir William Scot of Thirlstan; and congratulatory poems addressed to Auchinleck, one of which praises him as a man "Who dare be honest in degen'rate time/ When kind reproof's thought rude if not a crime."
Material related to his profession as a lawyer and judge includes commissions by the Earl of Galloway; his nominations to be Sheriff of Wigtown and a Lord of the Court of Sessions; his petition for admission to the Bar; and a short notebook of legal forms, among them the form of Tailzie, or entail.
Most of the correspondence remaining in Part II is also professional in nature, consisting of brief business notes, letters of congratulations on his official appointments, and comments on legal transactions and political alliances which shed light on Lord Auchinleck's position in the complex patronage systems of the period. The letters received from Robert Dundas, Lord Advocate of Scotland, reveal a long-standing friendship between the two men; in the earliest letter, Dundas addresses him as "Dear Sandy." In contrast, the correspondence of Lord Hyndford is filled with discussion of gardens and planting, and the letters were often sent with gifts of "Siberian Cedar Cones" and "Archangel red-and-white Turnip seeds" (Box 133, folder 2434-35).
Lord Auchinleck's interest in estate improvements was not limited to gardening, as the Estate Papers show. These include a summary account of expenses, 1754-79; bills and receipts for various charges, including some incurred through the building of the Manse; two folders of excambion contracts intended to regularize boundaries and remove land from runrig; and suits against delinquent tenants. Folder 2410 holds the records of the Birkieknaw coal works, built in 1767, and the Gasswater Lime and Coal Works. The first known mine on barony land, Birkieknaw produced 2,931 "loads" of coal in the first six months of 1768, which sold for £ 36.12.9. The Land Records for individual farms, located in folders 2791-2813, show the same attention and interest on a smaller scale.